Finding Aid for University of Michigan Center for Research on Economic Development Records 1956-1993
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
University of Michigan Center for Research on Economic Development records
1956-1993
1977-1993
University of Michigan. Center for Research on Economic Development.
9860 Bimu/2
Unit within the College of Literature Sciences & Arts at the University of Michigan established 1961 to conduct research and training on economic development in underdeveloped parts of the world. Papers document administration of the center and its research activities, most notably on West African countries.
6.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The record group was transferred on November 1997. (Donor no. 8653 )
The record group is open for research.
The Center for Research on Economic Development (CRED) was established in June 1961 as a research and training unit of the College of Literature, Science, and the Arts. Its early mandate was to conduct research and training on economic development in the underdeveloped regions of the world. Over time the Center established a reputation for research, advisory, and training activities in emerging countries in Africa.
A large percentage of CRED's research was conducted in field research projects. The majority of the field research was conducted in French-speaking Africa. In the early years the field research focused on the economic issues of rural communities, and in the later years the field research focused on policy issues. For the most part the recent research has concerned agricultural marketing, management, and reform in French-speaking Africa.
In 1988, CRED began sponsoring economic development conferences, held primarily in Africa. The conference topics included: economic advancement in Africa, economic reform, structural adjustment in Burundi, and global economic reform. These conferences and workshops were attended by senior African civil servants and policy researchers.
In 1980, CRED began offering its Seminar on Economic Development. The seminar was a seven-week program which taught economics in French. Most of the students came from ten African nations. As a part of the seminar there were guest lecturers in economic analysis, training in computer applications, and instruction in English. The students supplemented their education with field trips to industrial, agricultural, and governmental organizations in southern Michigan, as well as a visit to Washington, DC.
CRED received most of its institutional support from the University of Michigan. Most of its external income was derived from contracts with United States Agency for International Development for research services. In the past, the Ford Foundation and the Rockefeller Foundation provided institutional and project support.
It is believed that the Center was in existence until 1993, when it was subsumed as part of the International Institute, which was established in September 1993. Currently the Center is generally inactive.
Directors of the Center
1961-1963 Samuel P. Hayes
1963-1969 Wolfgang Stolper
1970-1977 Elliot Berg
1978-1981 Henri Josserand
1981-1982 Kenneth Shapiro (acting)
1982-1988 Robin Barlow
1988-1992 Ernest J. Wilson, III
1992-1993 Mark Gersovitz
The record group is made up of five series: Administration, Projects, Project Proposals, Research and Seminar on Economic Development.
The Center for Research on Economic Development record group is comprised primarily of the records of the research proposed and conducted by the Center and the administrative work required to conduct the research. The bulk of the materials covers the years from 1977 to 1993. Some of the documents in this collection are in the French language, since much of their research and work was conducted in and concerned Francophone countries in Africa.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Center for Research on Economic Development.; University of Michigan--Research.; Africa--Economic policy.; Economic Development.
- Administration, 1959-1992
  The first series, Administration (Boxes 1-3) contains annual reports, correspondence, and budgets for the Center. Interesting documents in this series include the correspondence between the Center and universities in France and the Ivory Coast, and a collection of historical papers on the development of the Center in the late 1950s. Also contained in this series are the records relating to the Foster Library which was managed by the Center. Contained in the Library's records are the lists of the many publications that the Center published from their research.
  - Annual Reports, 1965-1990; 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Ariza-Nino, Edgar, 1977-1983 (Box 1)
    (Some documents in French)
  - Barlow, Robin, 1992-1993 (Box 1)
  - Berg, Elliot, 1977-1980 (Box 1)
  - Budgets
    - 1960-1993 (Box 1)
    - Core Support, 1976-1983 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1980-1993 (Box 1)
  - Contracts, 1969-1993 (Box 1)
  - Department Review, 1977-1983 (Box 1)
  - Economic Development Doctorate Proposal, 1959-1961 (Box 1)
  - Economics Course Syllabi, 1960-1962 (Box 1)
  - Elias, Christine, 1990-1992 (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee, 1974-1991; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Fellowships, 1983-1991 (Box 1)
  - Food Policy/ Senegal Conference, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Funding
    - Ford Foundation, 1962-1981; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Rockefeller Foundation, 1968-1981 (Box 1)
  - Foster Library, 1962-1993; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - General Correspondence, 1971-1992; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Gersovitz, Mark, 1990-1993 (Box 1)
  - Gish, Oscar, 1982-1983 (Box 2)
  - History, 1956-1992 (Box 2)
  - Incoming Fax, January-July, 1993; 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Letters of Support for Program, 1992 (Box 2)
  - Linkages with Clermont-Fer, 1979-1993; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Linkages with University of Abidjan, 1979-1988 (Box 2)
  - Linkages with University of Michigan, 1990-1992 (Box 2)
  - Makinen, Marty, 1980-1982 (Box 2)
  - Midwest Conference on Economic Development, 1979; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Newspaper Articles, circa 1982-1983 (Box 2)
  - Outgoing Fax, January-August, 1993 (Box 2)
  - Porter, Richard, 1977-1982 (Box 2)
  - Relationships with Organizations, 1972-1993; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Seminars, 1973-1977 (Box 2)
  - Shapiro, Kenneth, 1979-1983 (Box 2)
  - Steedman, Charles, 1970-1993; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan International Development Program, 1977 (Box 2)
  - USAID Review, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Vietnamese Delegation Visit, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Visitors, 1977-1992; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Wilson, Paul, undated-April 1993; 2 folders (Box 3)
- Projects, 1982-1993
  The second series, Projects, (Boxes 3 and 4) contains the correspondence, contracts and reports for those projects, between 1982 and 1993, for which the Center submitted the winning proposal. The two most significant projects in this series are The Gambia Agricultural Research and Diversification project and the Niger Agricultural Sector Development grant. These projects were running almost simultaneously, with the project in The Gambia active between 1986-1990 and the project in Niger active from 1985 to 1991. Many of the projects in the Projects series can be also found in the planning and proposal stages in the Project Proposals and Research series.
  - Agricultural Surveys and Policy Analysis-Rwanda, 1989-1991 (Box 3)
  - Democracy in Africa
    - General, 1992-1993 (Box 3)
    - Impact of Regulation on Economic Performance, 1992-1993 (Box 3)
    - Role of Professional Business Associations, 1993 (Box 3)
  - Economic Reform in Africa-Seminar, Abidjan, 1988 (Box 3)
  - Economic Reform in Africa-Seminar, Nairobi, 1988 (Box 3)
  - Economic Reform in Africa-Workshop, Nairobi, 1989-1990; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - The Gambia Agricultural Research and Diversification
    - Annual Workplans, 1986-1989 (Box 3)
    - Contract, 1986 (Box 3)
    - Contract Revisions, 1987-1989 (Box 3)
    - Finances, 1986-1990 (Box 3)
    - General Correspondence, 1984-1989; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Personnel, 1986-1989 (Box 3)
    - Project Evaluations, 1989 (Box 3)
    - Reports
      - General, 1986-1989 (Box 3)
      - Quarterly, 1986-1989 (Box 3)
  - The Gambia Financial and Private Enterprise Support, 1993 (Box 3)
  - The Gambia River Basin Studies, 1982-1988 (Box 3)
  - Global Economic Reform-Workshop, Ann Arbor, 1989-1990; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Madagascar Telecommunications and Transport, 1992-1993 (Box 3)
  - Niger Agricultural Sector Development
    - Contracts
      - Abt Associates, 1985-1991 (Box 3)
      - Tufts University, 1986-1990 (Box 3)
      - USAID
        - 1984-1990 (Box 4)
        - Correspondence, 1985-1992; 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Evaluations, 1986; 1989; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - General Correspondence, 1985-1993; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Personnel, 1985-1992; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Reports
      - Expenditures, 1985-1992; 3 folders (Box 4)
      - General, undated, 1991-1993 (Box 4)
      - Monthly Activity, 1986-1991; 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Semi-Annual, 1989-1990 (Box 4)
    - Short-Term Technical Assistance, 1985; 1990-1991 (Box 4)
  - Population and Development in Burundi, 1987 (Box 4)
  - Structural Policy Analysis-Workshop, Burundi, 1990-1991 (Box 4)
  - U.S. African Trade Case Studies, 1991 (Box 4)
- Project Proposals, 1983-1992
  The third series, Project Proposals (Boxes 4-6) contains general, technical, and cost proposals for proposal requests announced by the United States Agency for International Development or other funding organizations. These proposals provide a wealth of information about the Center's plans for meeting project goals, and the Center's available resources. The proposals are especially useful for a comparison between the information contained in the proposal and the actual project as it was executed, contained in the Projects series. It should be noted that not every proposal submitted resulted in the grant of a project. In those cases where the Center's proposal was unsuccessful, this is explained in the accompanying correspondence.
  - Africa Democracy and Governance Project, 1991 (Box 4)
    (1 of 2 folders)
  - Africa Democracy and Governance Project, 1991 (Box 5)
    (2 of 2 folders)
  - Agricultural Policy Implementation Project-Tunisia, 1987; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Cameroon Agricultural Policy and Planning, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Case Study, "Ralandia,", 1986 (Box 5)
  - Chad Agricultural Marketing and Technology Transfer, 1991 (Box 5)
  - Development and Reconstruction of Lebanon, 1983 (Box 5)
  - Enhancing Policy Reform Capacity in Sub-Saharan Africa, 1988 (Box 5)
  - The Gambia Agricultural Research and Diversification, 1984 (Box 5)
  - The Gambia Financial and Private Enterprise Support, 1992 (Box 5)
  - Global Economic Reform Workshop, 1991 (Box 6)
  - Guinea Smallholder Production, 1984 (Box 6)
  - Niger Agricultural Sector Development Grant, 1985 (Box 6)
  - Niger Policy Analysis and Monitoring Project, 1991 (Box 6)
  - Sociological and Economic Considerations of Agroforestry in Niger, 1984 (Box 6)
  - Structural Adjustment and Policy Reform in Senegal, 1988 (Box 6)
  - Vietnam Exchange Program, 1988 (Box 6)
- Research, 1977; 1983-1993
  The fourth series, Research (Box 6) contains the preliminary work and correspondence done on behalf of the Center's project proposals or other research interests. The majority of the research dates from the late 1980s and the early 1990s. Many of the papers here can be followed from the research stage, through the proposal stage, and often into the project stage.
  - Burundi Enterprise Support and Training, 1990-1991 (Box 6)
  - Chad Agricultural Marketing and Technology Transfer, 1991 (Box 6)
  - Democracy and Governance for Africa, 1991 (Box 6)
  - Democracy in Africa
    - General, 1991-1992 (Box 6)
    - Impact of Regulation on Economic Performance, 1992 (Box 6)
    - Role of Professional Business Associations, 1992 (Box 6)
  - Doing Business in Developing Economies, 1993 (Box 6)
  - Economic Liberalization in Sub-Saharan Africa, 1987 (Box 6)
  - Economic Regulation Case Studies, 1992 (Box 6)
  - Environmental and Natural Resources Policy and Training, 1991 (Box 6)
  - The Gambia Financial and Private Enterprise Support, 1992 (Box 6)
  - Guinea Natural Resources Management, 1992 (Box 6)
  - Madagascar Initiative, 1990-1992 (Box 6)
  - Nigerian Economic Management, 1988 (Box 6)
  - Potential Research Opportunities, 1990-1993 (Box 6)
  - Priorities for Professional Education in Mali, 1987-1988 (Box 6)
  - Public Policy in Niger, 1991-1992 (Box 6)
  - Research Proposal Guidelines, 1973; 1980 (Box 6)
  - Role of the Private Sector on Economic Reform, 1989-1990 (Box 6)
  - Structural Adjustment Policies-Workshop, Burundi, 1989-1990 (Box 6)
  - Tax Policy, 1991 (Box 6)
  - Technical Assistance for Macroeconomic and International Economic Analysis, 1992 (Box 6)
  - Togo Agricultural Policy Reform, 1987 (Box 6)
  - Undeveloped Projects, 1989-1992 (Box 6)
  - West Bank/ Gaza Human Resource Development, 1980 (Box 6)
  - Zaire Agricultural Policy and Planning, circa 1990 (Box 6)
- Seminar on Economic Development, 1983-1993
  The fifth series, Seminar on Economic Development (Box 7) is the smallest series in the record group. This series contains the papers for the annual seminar sponsored by the Center and held in Ann Arbor. Since the seminar was conducted exclusively in French, the majority of the papers in this series are in the French language. The most useful papers in this series are the lists of participants, because they provide a great deal of information about the occupations of the attendees and their countries of origin. The rest of the papers in the series are instructive for understanding how an international seminar is organized and executed.
  - Applications and Acceptances, 1991-1993 (Box 7)
  - Budget and Invoices, 1991-1993 (Box 7)
  - Evaluations, 1990-1992 (Box 7)
  - General Correspondence, 1990-1993 (Box 7)
  - Newsletter mailing lists, 1991-1992 (Box 7)
  - Participant Lists and Responses, 1986-1991 (Box 7)
  - Photographs, circa 1993 (Box 7)
  - Program Notes, 1990-1991 (Box 7)
  - Syllabi, 1991-1993 (Box 7)
  - Washington D.C. Field Trip, 1991-1992 (Box 7)